{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "President and position required. The first holder of this position under this president earned a nickname during the selection process for the state flower of Texas. The second holder of this position also served as Secretary of Agriculture under this same president. The third holder of this position held it for less than a year after being nominated to it in an event called the “Second Missouri Compromise.” For ten points, what is this position that John Garner, Henry Wallace, and Harry Truman held under this president?",
      "answer": [
        "Vice President of Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
        "FDR A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these places in Minsk, called “The Pit,” shows a group of people descending a staircase. Another one of these places in Germany has a constantly looping video of two men kissing. The newest of these installations in the Tiergarten has a memorial pool in the shape of a wheel, with a triangle in the center, and honors the Romani people. For ten points, name these commemorative public art institutions, the largest of which is Berlin’s Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe.",
      "answer": [
        "Holocaust Memorials",
        "equivalents for memorial, such as monument",
        "statues"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While in Sweden, this person learned Swedish to work with Anders Bruzelius on civil procedure. In Frontiero v. Richardson, this person argued that Air Force Lieutenant Sharron Frontiero could claim her husband as a “dependent.” Replacing Byron White in 1993, this person authored an opinion on gender discrimination at the Virginia Military Institute. For ten points, name this woman who died in September, 2020, the second female Supreme Court justice.",
      "answer": [
        "Ruth Bader Ginsburg",
        "R.B.G. D4 This man refused to visit victims of the Great Mississippi Flood due to his belief that it would be political grandstanding. Democrat John W. Davis and Progressive Robert LaFollette both lost an election to this man. This man responded to a Samuel Gompers telegram by claiming that “there is no right to strike against public safety,” gaining national attention for his suppression of the Boston Police Strike. For ten points, name this “silent” president who succeeded Warren Harding. ANSWER: Calvin Coolidge"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A novel about a folk hero from this country has a style that parallels that title character’s Jerilderie Letter. Another novel by an author from this country focuses on a man who received the title “Righteous Among Nations” at the Yad Vashem Memorial for his efforts in convincing German authorities that he needed to hire Jews during World War Two. For ten points, name this home country of the author of Schindler’s Ark, Thomas Keneally, and of the bushranger Ned Kelly.",
      "answer": "Commonwealth of Australia T"
    },
    {
      "question": "At a World War One battle off the coast of this country, the SMS Emden quickly sank the Zhemchug and Mousquet. A region in this country includes an island once named for the Prince of Wales and a capital city named for George III, George Town. The Battle of Penang took place in what is now this country in the Strait of Malacca. Tunku Abdul Rahman was the first Prime Minister of, for ten points, F what Asian country that expelled Singapore in 1965?",
      "answer": "Malaysia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Three days after this event, a ceremony was held that is depicted in the painting The Distribution of the Eagle Standards. Pope Pius VII was present at this event, three years after signing a Concordat with this event’s central figure. This event took place at Notre Dame Cathedral instead of the traditional Reims [RONCE], and a David [dah-VEED] painting of this event depicts a kneeling Josephine. For ten A points, name this December 2, 1804 event in which a Frenchman crowned himself emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Coronation of Napoleon",
        "descriptions of Napoleon becoming emperor"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first Naval Reserve Officer Training Corps was established at this university by Chester Nimitz. A memorial for James Rector was held in this university’s Sproul Plaza after a violent protest at its People’s Park. The Symbionese Liberation Army kidnapped Patty Hearst while she studied at this university. This university is named for an idealist Anglo-Irish philosopher and is known for its activism during the Free Speech Movement. For ten points, name this public California university. R",
      "answer": "University of California, Berkeley"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist wrote and recorded the song “Happy Birthday” to advocate for Martin Luther King, Jr. Day becoming a federal holiday. This musician’s “classic period” was from 1972 to 1977, when he released the albums Talking Book and Songs in the Key of Life. This man acknowledged influential Black musicians in the song “Sir Duke” and became the youngest ever to top the charts at age 13 in 1963. For ten points, name this influential R&B musician who wrote “For Once in My Life” and “Superstition.”",
      "answer": [
        "Stevie Wonder",
        "Stevland Hardaway Morris",
        "Stevland Hardaway Judkins D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man placed a likeness of his own head onto the Colossus of Nero and declared that he was the “only left handed fighter to conquer twelve times one thousand men.” Twenty-five consuls were appointed in a single year after this man’s advisor Cleander sold public offices. This man was strangled by the wrestler Narcissus after the Plebeian games, where he had slain hundreds of beasts in an attempt to identify as Hercules. For ten points, identify this emperor, the son of Marcus Aurelius.",
      "answer": "Commodus T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s biggest library has an angular glass ceiling covered in diamond girders designed by Rem Koolhaas. This city’s neighborhood of Northgate contFains one of the first malls and is the site of an NHL franchise planned for 2021. This city’s best known structure was built for the 1962 World’s Fair and can withstand forces as strong as the nearby 1700 Cascadia earthquake. For ten points, name this city, the birthplace of Jay Inslee and Bill Gates and the site of the Space Needle.",
        "answer": "Seattle, Washington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2020, Governor Jay Inslee told President Trump to “stay out of Washington State’s business” when Trump suggested Inslee should “take back” this Seattle neighborhood from protestors. A",
        "answer": [
          "Capital Hill Autonomous Zone",
          "CHAZ,"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismanandRobertNorrisweredisgracedafterafailedexpeditiontoLisbontosupportaPortuguese rebellion against Philip II. This man legendarily stated that he had plenty of time to finish a game of bowls at Plymouth Hoe before tackling an enemy fleet. This man was described as having “singed the king of Spain’s beard” in his attack on Cadiz that delayed the Spanish Armada. For ten points, name this English sea captain who circumnavigated the globe aboard the Golden Hind.",
        "answer": "Sir Francis Drake R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sir Francis Drake became the mayor of this port city on the south coast of Devon from which the Pilgrim Fathers later departed for the New World.",
        "answer": "Plymouth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a book titled for this man’s “Black Box,” Michael Behe coined the term “irreducible complexity” to argue against this man’s theories. This man’s theories are presented as “cranes” in a book by Daniel Dennet titled for this man’s “Dangerous Idea.” This man argued for the common ancestry of animals and D humans in Descent of Man. For ten points, name this man who outlined the theory of natural selection in On the Origin of Species.",
        "answer": "Charles Darwin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, known as “Darwin’s Bulldog,” engaged in a debate with Samuel Wilberforce in 1860 to help spread the ideas of evolution. This man also coined the word “agnosticism.”",
        "answer": "Thomas Henry Huxley T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Members of this ethnic group gathered at Bastion Point for a 1977 protest. A 1960s protest movement of these people arose after their land rights were restricted by their namesake Affairs Amendment Act, which was seen as a treacherous act of the Pakeha [PAH-kih-hah]. These people lost much of their land during the invasion of Waikato. These people signed the Treaty of Waitangi with the British on North F Island. For ten points, name these indigenous Polynesian people of New Zealand.",
        "answer": "Maori"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "First contact between the Maori and Europeans occurred in 1642 when this Dutch explorer unsuccessfully attempted to land in an area he named “Murderer’s Bay.”",
        "answer": "Abel Tasman A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This megacity, more accurately referred to as an “urban agglomeration,” became the capital of its colony in 1914 and continued as capital after its nation’s independence in 1960 until the capital moved in 1991. This city, south of Ibadan, is projected to double in size by 2050 to more than 16 million people. Movies like The Wedding Party were produced by this city’s “Nollywood” industry. For ten points, name this city with the largest metropolitan population in Africa, located in Nigeria.",
        "answer": "Lagos"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2015, this Doctor of Zoology became the first president of Nigeria to lose a presidential elecRtion and concede defeat when he was defeated by General Muhammadu Buhari.",
        "answer": "Goodluck Jonathan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Isaac Babel and Osip Mandelstam were among the writers targeted in this event, the latter of whom was sent to a labor camp after reciting an “Epigram” against its overseer. Special troikas carried out extrajudicial punishments during this period and were led by the NKVD. During this period Lev Kamenev and Grigory Zinoviev were among the men convicted during a series of show trials in Moscow. Lasting from 1936 to 1938, name this major crackdown on opposition under Stalin. D",
        "answer": [
          "Great Purge",
          "Great Terror, Year of ‘37,",
          "Yezhovschina"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joseph Stalin met for four days with Franklin Delano Roosevelt and Winston Churchill at the Soviet embassy in this Middle Eastern city in 1943.",
        "answer": "Teheran, Iran T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the end of this film, two of the main characters are surprised to find nobody picketing their office and walk in to find phones ringing uncontrollably. Richard Snipe approximates that 90 people were involved in the central crime depicted in this film. Michael Rezendes is a Mark Ruffalo-portrayed reporter in this film which ends with a statement about the resignation of Cardinal Law. For ten points, name this F Best Picture-winning film about the Boston Globe investigation of child abuse by priests.",
        "answer": "Spotlight"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mark Ruffalo also appeared in this 2007 film that tells the story of a still uncaught serial murderer who claimed to have murdered 37 people in the San Francisco area in the 1960s and 70s.",
        "answer": "Zodiac A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man reestablished the Independent Treasury System and reduced the rates set by the Black Tariff by signing the Walker Tariff. This man had the shortest presidential retirement, surviving only three months after leaving office, and was the only president who was previously Speaker of the House. The rallying cry “54-40 or fight” was used by supporters of this man in reference to the annexation of Oregon. For ten points, name this president who presided over the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "James Knox Polk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Walker Tariff was named for Robert J. Walker who held this cabinet position under Polk, a posRition previously held by Oliver Wolcott, Jr. and more recently held by Steven Mnuchin.",
        "answer": "Secretary of the Treasury"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Colonial American-Indian Conflicts",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American theater of the Seven Years War that ended with the Treaty of Paris of 1763 F",
          "answer": "French and Indian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederacy of six Native American tribes in New York that fought in the Beaver Wars",
          "answer": [
            "Iroquois",
            "Haudenosaunee"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1763 uprising in the Great Lakes Region named for an Ottawa leader that began with the siege of Fort Detroit A",
          "answer": [
            "Pontiac’s War",
            "Pontiac’s Rebellion",
            "Pontiac’s Conspiracy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1636-38 conflict whose namesake tribe fought against the Plymouth and Massachusetts Bay",
          "answer": "Pequot War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wampanoag leader who fought a namesake 1675-78 war against British colonists",
          "answer": [
            "King Philip",
            "Metacomet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederacy of Algonquian-speaking tribes who killed 347 people in the Jamestown massacre R",
          "answer": "Powhatan Confederacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe who fought a namesake war from 1711-13 in North Carolina",
          "answer": "Tuscarora"
        },
        {
          "question": "1715-16 war in which the namesake tribe killed hundreds of traders in South Carolina around the Savannah River",
          "answer": "Yamasee War D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Charles II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Lord Protector and Parliamentarian leader whose death allowed for the restoration of Charles II F",
          "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion he converted to on his deathbed whose recusants were persecuted",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Brother who succeeded him, overthrown in the Glorious Revolution",
          "answer": "James II A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Philosopher who wrote Leviathan and tutored him in mathematics",
          "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country against whom he fought two wars in an alliance with Louis XIV",
          "answer": [
            "Netherlands",
            "Spain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Document allowing for greater religious tolerance that he was forced to replace with the first of the Test Acts R",
          "answer": "Royal Declaration of Indulgence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protestant conspiracy that attempted to assassinate him and his brother in 1683",
          "answer": "Rye House plot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tree in which he hid after his defeat at the Battle of Worcester",
          "answer": "Royal Oak D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Chile",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city destroyed and rebuilt in a 1647 earthquake F",
          "answer": "Santiago"
        },
        {
          "question": "Marxist president who committed suicide during a military coup at La Moneda Palace",
          "answer": "Salvador Allende"
        },
        {
          "question": "Authoritarian dictator who implemented economic reforms under the direction of the Chicago Boys",
          "answer": "Augusto Pinochet A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conflict it won against Peru and Bolivia, cutting off the latter’s access to a namesake body of water",
          "answer": [
            "War of the Pacific",
            "Saltpeter War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Independence leader who won the Battle of Chacabuco over Spanish forces alongside Jose de San Martin",
          "answer": "Bernardo O’Higgins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police that assassinated Orlando Letellier R",
          "answer": [
            "DINA",
            "Direccion de Inteligencia Nacional",
            "National Intelligence Directorate"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Family that dominated the Patria Vieja period whose member Jose Miguel governed it before the Spanish reconquest",
          "answer": "Carrera"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following the Holocaust, these institutions became refuges for Jewish intellectuals such as Ernst Borinski, who began working at one oFf these institutions in Tougaloo, Mississippi. After losing his right arm at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Seven Pines, a Union general known as the “Christian general” founded one of these institutions in Washington, D.C. A number of these institutions were funded by the Second Morrill Act, including one in (10 pts)",
        "Alabama where the Tuskegee Airmen trained and attended classes. For ten points, name these institutions which include Morehouse College and Howard University."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Historically Black Colleges and Universities",
        "HBCUs,",
        "answers containing both",
        "either of Colleges",
        "Universities A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man created earldoms for his brothers, Gyrth and Leofwine, and was on good terms with Stigand, the archbishop of Canterbury. After this man was captured by Guy of Ponthieu, he joined his chief rival on a campaign in Brittany. (20 pts)",
        "Tostig, this man’s brother, won at Gate Fulford with the help of a rival of this man with the epithet “Hardrada.” This man’s sister Edith married Edward the Confessor, and this man was (10 pts)",
        "crowned the day after Edward’s death. For ten points, who is this king of England who after winning at Stamford Bridge was defeated at the Battle of Hastings by William of Normandy? ANRSWER: Harold Godwinson (accept Harold II) (3) This person’s great uncle was Lebanese-American historian Philip Hitti, who pioneered Arabic studies in the U.S. Barbara Morgan served as backup for this person, who was to present two 15 minute (+) classes, including “Where We’ve Been, Where We’re Going, Why” and “The Ultimate Field Trip.” Nebraska honors this educator with a namesake award for courage. Part of a team including Francis (*) Scobee and Judith Resnick, this woman died after rubber O-rings failed, leading to a catastrophic explosion. For ten points, name this astronaut and teacher who died in the Challenger disaster. D"
      ],
      "answer": "Christa McAuliffe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader gave a speech in which he encouraged revolution by instructing civilians to “turn every house into a fort.” The death of Zahurul Haq led to this leader’s acquittal in the Agartala Conspiracy. This leader commanded the Rakkhi Bahini private militias to enforce a one-party state under his (20 pts)",
        "Awami League. Operation Searchlight targeted this man’s country, which underwent a major famine in 1974. This man is popularly known as (10 pts)",
        "“Bangabandhu,” and his daughter became Prime Minister of their nation thirty-seven years after this man left office. For ten points, name this first post-independence president of Bangladesh."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sheikh Mujibur Rahman",
        "Sheikh Mujib T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this period, the Jisha-Bungyo, the highest ranking of the three administrators, was tasked with overseeing temples. The Okamoto Daihachi incident caused a leader in this period to ban (20 pts)",
        "Christianity. Thousands of foreign traders were executed during this period in the aftermath of the Shimabara Rebellion. A work by Jason Josephson-Storm F posits that Japan had no concept of religion until after the Black Ships of (10 pts)",
        "Admiral Matthew Perry appeared, forcing the government to open its ports during this period. For ten points, name this feudal military government, the last shogunate of Japan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tokugawa Shogunate",
        "“Period” in place of “Shogunate,”",
        "Edo Shogunate"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Abraham Mendel Theben used his influence with this ruler to exonerate Jews accused of blood libel. This monarch appointed Gerard von Swieten to investigate the supposed spread A of vampires in her kingdom. This monarch’s advisor, the Prince of (20 pts)",
        "Kaunitz, engineered the switching of alliances in the Diplomatic Revolution. Frederick the Great invaded this ruler’s territory of (10 pts)",
        "Silesia, sparking the War of Austrian Succession. For ten points, name this Austrian empress guaranteed the throne by her father’s Pragmatic Sanction."
      ],
      "answer": "Maria Theresa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Water was originally trapped in this lake by mudflows caused by the eruption of Mount Pluto. The region around this lake was inhabited by the Washoe, and Cave Rock on this lakRe’s shore is considered sacred. This lake has had many names, including Lake (20 pts)",
        "Bigler and Fremont’s Lake, after the first Euro-American to see it. Ski areas on this lake include Heavenly Mountain Resort and (10 pts)",
        "Squaw Valley, the site of the 1960 Winter Olympics. For ten points, name this largest alpine lake in North America, located on the California-Nevada border."
      ],
      "answer": "Lake Tahoe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Union general with this surname was promoted to major general after Gettysburg for his defense of Little Round Top and had the first name Gouvernor. Jonathan Trumbull Ddepicted the death of a man with this surname at Breed’s Hill. (20 pts)",
        "Joseph was an American commander at Bunker Hill with this surname, which also belongs to a man who served three terms as governor of California before taking over Fred (10 pts)",
        "Vinson’s seat on the Supreme Court. That man also wrote the majority opinions in Loving v. Virginia and Miranda v. Arizona. For ten points, what surname do these people share?"
      ],
      "answer": "Warren T"
    }
  ]
}